Finding Aid for Mary S. Coleman Papers 1938-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary S. Coleman Papers 1938-1984, 1972-1982
Coleman, Mary S., 1914-
3 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
Battle Creek attorney, justice, later chief justice of the Michigan Supreme Court. Correspondence, clippings, speeches, and topical files relating primarily to the ceremonial, out-of-court, responsibilities of a supreme court justice, and to her election campaigns in 1971 and 1980; also files concerning her interest in juvenile justice and the reapportionment of the Michigan Legislature and miscellaneous photographs.
8596 AC; Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated to the library by the Honorable Mary S. Coleman (donor no. 7011 ) in October 1983 and December 1985.
The collection is open for research.
Mary S. Coleman, born in Forney, Texas, received her BA Degree from the University of Maryland in 1935, and her Juris Doctor Degree from George Washington University in 1939.
After raising two daughters and then practicing law with her husband, Creighton, in Battle Creek, Michigan, Coleman was elected probate and juvenile judge in Calhoun County in 1960. For twelve years, she demonstrated her keen interest in youth by establishing new judicial juvenile procedures. In 1972, she became the first woman to be elected a justice of the Michigan Supreme Court, and in 1979 she received further recognition when her fellow justices elected her chief justice. She ran for and won reelection in 1980, was elected chief justice for a second time, and served on Michigan's high court until her retirement in 1982.
Throughout her judicial career, Judge Coleman gained the respect and admiration of her peers in Michigan and around the country. For several years, she was under consideration for possible appointment to the U.S. Supreme Court; she was the recipient of many honorary degrees and awards; and she was asked to participate in a wide range of professional and non-professional activities.
The Mary S. Coleman Collection is arranged by series or topic: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Miscellaneous Topical File; Speeches; Supreme Court Topical Files; Miscellaneous; and Visual Materials. While a portion of the collection contains pre-1972 material, the bulk concerns the 1972-1982 period during which Judge Coleman served on the Michigan Supreme Court.
Subjects:
Apportionment (Election law)--Michigan.; Coleman, Mary S. (Mary Stallings), 1914-2001; Elections--Michigan--1972.; Elections--Michigan--1980.; Judges--Michigan.; Juvenile delinquency--Michigan.; Lawyers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Women judges--Michigan.; Women lawyers--Michigan--Battle Creek.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Coleman, Creighton R., 1912-; Coleman, Mary S. (Mary Stallings), 1914-2001; Germany.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Prison facilities.; Women.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1960-1961 relating to election to Probate and Juvenile Court (Volume 1)
    - 1972 contains clippings, photographs, and campaign materials from, 1972 campaign (Volume 2)
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Undated 1960-August 1980, 49 folders (Box 1)
    - September 1980-1984, 67 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - 1972-August 1975, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - September 1975-June 1982, 24 folders (Box 3)
    - July 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Personal
    - 1973-1981, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Supreme Court
    - Elections and Reelections
      - 1972 (Election to Supreme Court) (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Chief Justice Election, sample congratulatory messages) (Box 4)
      - 1980, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Legislative Matters 1973-1979 (Box 4)
    - New York State Courts 1979 (Box 4)
      (regarding trip)
    - Retirement (samples) (Box 4)
    - Speaking Engagements 1981 (samples) (Box 4)
    - U.S. Supreme Court Appointment 1973-1981 (Box 4)
      (mostly letters of recommendation, and Coleman's responses)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Topical File
  - Crime Prevention Center 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Educational Needs of Youth (Advisory Committee) 1963 (Box 4)
  - Juvenile Justice, 1974 (Box 4)
  - National Conference on "The Causes of Popular Dissatisfaction With the Administration of Justice" materials 1976 (Box 4)
    (includes copy of Justice Coleman's remarks as discussion leader)
  - Prisons (Box 4)
    (mostly re: the Detroit House of Corrections)
  - Reapportionment of the Michigan Legislature 1982, 7 folders (Box 5)
    (mostly bills, plans, etc.)
  - Retirement Luncheon (Box 5)
    (Children's Charter of the Courts of Michigan, Scrapbook material)
- Speeches
  Of primary interest to the researcher should be the speeches of Judge Coleman, in which she presents her views on topics ranging from juvenile justice to the progress of women in America. The personal folder, clippings files, and general and personal correspondence all provide insight into the personal side of Mary Coleman's life. There is little in the collection regarding the Judge's views on specific legal cases and issues since for her to write or speak of them, in detail, ran the risk of having to disqualify herself from deciding cases on matters about which she had already expressed a public opinion.
  - Undated 1973-1976, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1977-1984, 6 folders (Box 6)
- Supreme Court Topical Files 1973-1982
  - Administrative and Court Management, Inc., report 1980 (Box 6)
  - Einar Bohlin, court administrator (largely correspondence and reports) 1979-1980, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Russel Bough, court administrator (largely correspondence and reports) 1982, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Circuit Court Judges 1980-1982 (Box 6)
  - Commission on Observance of International Women's Year 1975 (Box 7)
  - Court of Appeals 1979-1981 (Box 7)
  - Court Financing 1979-1983 primarily, 1980, 1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Court Reorganization 1980 (Box 7)
  - Deaf Interpretation 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - Double Jeopardy (Box 7)
  - Foster Care Review Board 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Friends of the Court 1982 (Box 7)
  - Juvenile Affairs (Juvenile Code Revision) 1974-1979, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Michigan Judicial Institute 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - Probate Code and Rules 1979 (Box 7)
  - Retreat 1980 (Box 7)
  - Retroactivity (Box 7)
  - Standards for termination of Parental Rights 1980 (Box 7)
  - State Appellate Defender 1979-1982 (Box 7)
  - State Assumption of Judiciary Costs 1980 (Box 7)
  - State Bar Circuit Court Docket Survey 1976, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Substance Abuse Services (Advisory Committee) 1976 (Box 7)
  - Swainson, Justice John B. (correspondence with and regarding) 1975 (Box 7)
  - Television in the Courtroom 1979-1982 (Box 7)
  - Traffic Courts 1979-1981 (Box 7)
  - Wayne County Juvenile Court 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Wayne County Probate Court 1978-1980, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Women's First Political Caucus 1973 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Awards and Honorary Materials, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Coleman Commission Report on Permanency Planning 1985 (Box 8)
  - Ike (Eisenhower) Day Committee Co-Chairman for Michigan 1956 (materials relating to) (Box 8)
  - Probate and Juvenile Judge (materials relating to her career as) 1960-1972 (Box 8)
  - Ronald Reagan's 1984 Campaign in Michigan (materials relating to) (Box 8)
  - Travel reminiscences, post-World War II Europe (Box 8)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - Awards and Honors, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Campaigns 1972, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Children's Charter of the Courts of Michigan 1971, 1981, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Early Photographs (Box 8)
      (Includes her performance in "The Heiress" with the Battle Creek Civic Theater in 1950)
    - European Trip. Post WW II travels with Creighton Coleman (Volume 3)
    - Family Photographs (Box 8)
      (Includes Creighton Coleman (husband), daughters Leslie and Carol, and grandchildren)
    - Groups-Identified and Unidentified (Box 8)
    - International Women's Year 1975 (Box 8)
      (Includes two photographs of President Gerald R. Ford)
    - Michigan Supreme Court, formal portraits 1972-1982 (Box 8)
      (includes swearing in of Mary S. Coleman and her swearing in of Lucille Watts, Coleman Young, and Norman Stockmeyer)
    - Miscellaneous. Snapshots and informal shots, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Milliken, William Grawn (Box 8)
    - Portraits-Old painting by Mary Holmes; 1980 Dedication in State Bar Building, Lansing (Box 8)
    - Portraits-Photographic; as Supreme Court Justice 1972-1980 (Box 8)
    - Tour of Southern Michigan Prison, Jackson 1975 (Box 8)
    - Probate and Juvenile Court members and activities (Box 8)
    - Speaking Engagement and Dedications (Box 8)
  - Videocassette
    - Interview on "Off The Record" program 1979 (Michigan State University Television), U-matic videotape; 30 min. (Box 8)